<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the Merchant Aduenturers charter from henceforth to be put in practise or execution, either within the kingdome, or beyond the seas</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1614-12-02</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100816</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836643</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836643</idno>
            <idno type="VID">927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22107)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 832:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the Merchant Aduenturers charter from henceforth to be put in practise or execution, either within the kingdome, or beyond the seas</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1614-12-02</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] sheets   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1614]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Newmarket the second day of December, in the twelfth yeere of our raigne ..</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Company of Merchant Adventurers of England --  Law and legislation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:927:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the British royal family encircled by the order of the garter and topped by a rose and a thistle</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAY Y PENSE</q>
                  </head>
               </figure> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Proclamation prohibiting the Merchant Aduenturers Charter from henceforth to be put in practiſe or execution, either within the Kingdome, or beyond the Seas.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there is no great action, which tendeth to the aduancement of a</hi> publique good, but it requireth certaine degrees of timely proceeding, and neuertheleſſe meeteth with diuers impediments; ſome by accident, and ſome by practiſe: So is there nothing that doeth more adorne the true Maieſtie and greatneſſe of Soueraigne Princes, then to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in their wel-grounded Reſolutions, and by their policie and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full power, to ſcatter and beat downe all difficulties, and vndue oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vntil they haue conducted their Actions to a good and happy end: Wee therefore, hauing propounded vnto Our ſelues; as a principall worke of Our times, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deine and prouide, that the great commoditie of Broad-cloth, being one of the principall Dowries of Our Kingdome, may receiue the due Manufactures of Dying and Dreſſing within the Realme; did to that end publiſh Our Royall Proclamation, dated the three and twentieth day of <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, prohibiting and ordeyning, That no Broad-cloth, of what ſort ſoeuer, made here within this Our Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be Exported Vndied and Vndreſt, after the ſecond day of <hi>Nouember</hi> next enſuing the date of Our ſaid Proclamation: Which time was giuen, aſwell for the Merchant Aduenturers, to vent their Whites, which might be vpon their hands, as for the preparing of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers things, neceſſary to the ſetling of the new Trade of Died and dreſſed Clothes. And We did further by Our ſaid Proclamation promiſe <hi>in the Word of a King</hi> to all Our louing Subiects, that ſhould vndertake to Export the ſaid Broad-clothes in their true Manufactures, that neither the Charter of the Merchant Aduenturers, nor any other Licences or Diſpenſations by <hi>Non obſtantes,</hi> contrary to Our Lawes, heretofore granted by Vs, or any Our Predeceſſors, ſhould be any maner of preiudice, impeachment, diſturbance, or interruption to ſuch, as ſhould after the time aforeſaid vent the ſaid Clothes Died and Dreſſed, according to Our ſaid Royall Ordinance and conſtitution; but ſhould be from the ſaid ſecond day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> declared to be annihilated, &amp; made void to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes. At which time of the publiſhing of Our ſaid Proclamation, We did expect that the ſaid Charter of the Merchant Aduenturers ſhould, before the ſaid ſecond day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> haue bene in due forme of Law ſurrendred: But after, finding the ſaid Company of Merchant Aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to make difficulty concerning the Surrender of their Patent; We haue bene enforced through
<pb facs="tcp:927:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> their wilfulneſſe and inconformitie, aſwell to order a Legall courſe to be taken for the ouerthrowe of their ſaid Patent: as alſo to licenſe diuers of Our louing Subiects, that haue very worthily, and with great alacrity, vndertaken to ſet vp and manage the ſaid Trade of Dyed and Dreſſed Clothes, to export alſo Whites in the meane while, vntill ſuch time as the ſaid Patent of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Aduenturers ſhall be by iudgement euicted, and ſome reſpite of time afterwards, leſt there might haue enſued ſome ſtand of the vent of Cloth before the new Trade were ſetled: But for as much as the courſe of a iudiciall proceeding, though in a Caſe neuer ſo cleare &amp; plaine, muſt haue due formes &amp; times obſerued according to the rules of Law, &amp; for that time in this caſe is exceeding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and that it is not poſſible for the new intended Company, to goe on with that confidence and incouragement, that in ſo great a buſineſſe were fit, as long as the Charter of the Merchant-Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers is put in vre, and practiſe:</p>
            <p>Therefore to remoue and diſcharge all diſcouragements and impediments: Wee doe by theſe preſents prohibite, forbid, conſtitute and ordeine, That from henceforth the Charter of the ſaid Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant aduenturers, and all powers, Lycences, authorities, priuiledges, formes of gouernement contained in the ſame, or otherwiſe all vſages, holding of Courts, meetings, aſſemblies, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceedings, by colour or vertue thereof, together with all the dependances, be not from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth put in any manner of practiſe or execution, either in the parts beyond the Seas, or here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Our Kingdome. And to that end, Wee doe not onely notifie and publiſh this Our Royall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition and ordinance, aſwell to all Forreiners, as to all Our louing Subiects, to whom it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine: But doe furthermore ſtraitly and expreſly charge and commaund, aſwel the Gouernour, Deputie, or Deputies, and Aſſiſtants of the ſaid Company of the Merchant Aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, as the whole bodie of them, and alſo euery of them in particuler, and all their Factors, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and Miniſters, aſwell beyond the Seas, as on this ſide, within Our Kingdome and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; That from this time forwards, they doe in no wiſe preſume, directly or indirectly, to doe, performe, or execute any Trade, Traffique, or Marchandizing, into, or from any the Countryes, or places where the ſaid Merchant Aduenturers, are, or haue beene priuiledged, or any point or thing whatſoeuer, by vertue or colour of their ſaid Charter, or by vertue of any former treatie or treaties, betwixt any Our noble Progenitors, or Predeceſſors, and any Prince or Potentate, Citie or politique Gouernment, or former vſages, vpon paine of Our High indignation, impriſonment, and other pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, which by Our Lawes or Prerogatiue Royall, may bee inflicted vpon them: Letting them know, that We ſhall proceede againſt euery ſuch offender, as a contemner of Our Royall Commandement, and a diſturber of ſo excellent a worke, wherein We haue ſo farre declared Our ſelues for the Vniuerſall Weale, and comfort of Our people.</p>
            <p>Prouided neuertheleſſe, that where Our Treaſurer of England hath directed his Letters to the Officers of Our Cuſtome-houſe, and Ports, giuing libertie of importation, onely vntill the laſt of this preſent Moneth of <hi>December:</hi> That theſe preſents ſhall not any way countermaund the ſaid limitation of time ſo prefixed, &amp; no longer: But that the ſaid Merchant-Aduenturers, may during that time importe accordingly; any thing before in theſe preſents, to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at Our Court at Newmarket</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the ſecond day of December, in the twelfth yeere of Our Raigne of England, France, and Ireland, and of Scotland the eight and fourtieth.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. ANNO DOM. 1614.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
